Guide to the George Sterling Papers M0021
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George Sterling papers
1909-1942
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Blaettler, Rudolph
Bynner, Witter
Bender, Albert M. (Albert Maurice), 1866-1941
Sterling, George, 1869-1926
M0021
1 Linear Feet: 2 boxes
Provenance
The majority of the Sterling papers came to Stanford as a gift of Rudolf Blaettler, collector. The Bynner-Sterling correspondence is a gift of Witter Bynner. (Oct 1960)
Biographical / Historical
American poet and playwright George Sterling was born in Sag Harbor, N.Y. on December 1, 1869. He was educated on the East Coast and attended St. Charles College in Maryland. In 1896 he married Carrie Rand of Oakland, California, and from 1898 to 1908 he was private secretary to Frank C. Havens of that city.
Sterling's first volume of poems, “ Testimony of the Suns and Other Poems, was published in 1903. After that time, there were nine other volumes and a number of separate poems published. From 1908 to 1915, Sterling was one of the leaders of the artist colony at Carmel, California. He died on November 18, 1926, by his own hands.
Scope and Contents
The Sterling Papers date from 1909 to 1942 with the bulk of material falling between 1920 and 1926. Those dated 1946 are memorial items marking the twentieth anniversary of his death. The collection includes correspondence, literary typescripts and manuscripts, printed poems and songs, a galley proof, photographs and clippings. Some of the material is in photostat form from originals in the University of Pennsylvania Library. Correspondents include: Edwin Markham, Theodore Dreiser, Robinson and Una Jeffers and Witter Bynner.
Separated Materials
Death mask is stored with Special Collections framed pictures.
Provenance
Gift of Rudolph Blaettler, Witter Bynner, and Albert M. Bender.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Blaettler, Rudolph; Bynner, Witter; Bender, Albert M. (Albert Maurice), 1866-1941; Sterling, George, 1869-1926
- Series 1. Correspondence, Outgoing
  - Mrs. Breeze, 1909, Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2. Witter Bynner, 1912, Jul 21 -
  - 3. 1912, Aug 1 -
  - 4. 1912, Aug 6 -
  - 5. 1912, Aug 26 -
  - 6. 1912, Sept 11 -
  - 7. 1912, Sept 20 -
  - 8. 1912, Sept 28 -
  - 9. 1912, Oct 15 -
  - 10. 1912, Oct 18 -
  - 11. 1912, (? 26) -
  - 12. Ave (Sterling), 1912, Oct 26 -
  - 13. Witter Bynner, 1912, Oct 30 -
  - 14. 1913, Jan 12 -
  - 15. 1913, Oct 17 -
  - 16. Albert (Bender), 1913, Nov 24 -
  - 1. Theodore Dreiser, 1920, Feb 10 -; photostat. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 2. 1920, Oct 26 -
  - 3. 1922, Aug 24 -
  - 4. 1923, May 16 -
  - 5. Mrs. Margaret Cobb, 1923, Jun 20 -
  - 6. 1923, Jul 18 -
  - 7. 1923, Aug 21 -
  - 8., 1923, Sept 5 -; photostat & dup.
  - 9. 1923, Dec 4 -
  - 10. 1923, Dec 11 -
  - 11. 1924, Feb 12 -
  - 12. 1924, Apr 29 -
  - 13. 1924, May 28 -
  - 14. 1924, Jun 18 -
  - 15. Theodore Dreiser, 1924, Jun 27 -; photostat.
  - 16. Mrs. Margaret Cobb, 1924, Jul 5 -
  - 17. 1924, Sept 12 -
  - 18. Theodore Dresier, 1924, Sept 14 -; photostat.
  - 19. Mrs. Margaret Cobb, 1924, Oct 6 -
  - 20. 1924, Oct 31
  - 1. Mrs. Margaret Cobb, 1925, Jan 21 - (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 2. 1925, Mar 9 -
  - 3. Hal, 1925, Jun 5 -
  - 4. Margaret Cobb, 1925, Jun 24 -
  - 5. Hal, 1925, Jul 2 -
  - 6. Margaret Cobb, 1925, Jul 14 -
    General note
    5 ltrs to Hal discurd missing 3/7/77
  - 7. Margaret Cobb, 1925, Jul 15 -
  - 8. Hal, 1925, Jul 27 -
  - 9. 1925, Jul 28 -
  - 10. Margaret Cobb, 1925, Jul 29 -
  - 11. 1925, Sept 8 -
  - 12. 1925, Oct 26 -
  - 13. Albert (Bender), 1925, Nov 30 -
  - 14. Margaret Cobb, 1926, Jan 22 -
  - 15. Theodore Dreiser, 1926, Jan 24 -; photostat.
  - 16. 1926, Feb 13 -
  - 17. Margaret Cobb, 1926, Feb 16 -
  - 18. Theodore Dreiser, 1926, Feb 17 -; photostat.
  - 1. Theodore Dreiser, 1926, Mar 23 -; photostat. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 2. Margaret Cobb, misdated, 1926, Mar 29-1929
  - 3. Margaret Cobb, 1926, Apr 9 -
  - 4. 1926, Apr 18 -
  - 5. 1926, May 6 -
  - 6. Theodore Dreiser, 1926, May 24 -; photostat.
  - 7. Margaret Cobb, 1926, Jun 1 -
  - 8. Theodore Dreiser, 1926, Jul 26 -; photostat.
  - 9. Margaret Cobb, 1926, Aug 9 -
  - 10. 1926, Aug 10 -
  - 11. 1926, Sept 27 -
  - 12. Hal, undated; 2 slips of paper & photostats.
- Series 2. Correspondence, Incoming
  - 1. Witter Bynner - Brotherhood of Man, Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2. notes on Sterling's poems, Oct 31, 1960
  - 2a. Ina Coolbrith, undated; A.N.S.
  - 3. Theodore Dreiser, 2-Oct-20
  - 4. Oct 8, 1920.
  - 5. Oct 9, 1920.
  - 6. Nov 6, 1920.
  - 7. frag., unsigned., 21-Dec-20
  - 8. Jul 15, 1924.
  - 9. Jul 25, 1925.
  - 10. Feb 7, 1926.
  - 1. Harriet Monroe, 18-Mar-16 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  - 1. Edwin Markham, 18-May-11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 2. Jun 1, 1911.
  - 3. Aug 2, 1911.
  - 4. Edwin Markham, 9-Aug-11
  - 5. Jan 7, 1917.
  - 6. Feb 21, 1917.
  - 7. Mar 14, 1917.
  - 8. Jun 21, 1917.
  - 9. Jul 25, 1917.
  - 10. Aug 17, 1917.
  - 11. Dec 11, 1919.
  - 12. Apr 28, 1920.
  - 13. Oct 29, 1920.
  - 14. Jan 28, 1926.
  - 15. by sec., Morgan., undated
  - 16. Poems signed M., undated
  - 17. Edwin Markham, Sept 29, 1926; A.L.S.
  - Ina Coolbrith A. N. S., undated (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  - Thomas R. Marshall T. N. S., 27-Dec-15 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  - Upton Sinclair A.N.S. & cover, 7-Feb-15 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  - 1. Robinson Jeffers, 5-Jul-24; Photostats. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2. Aug 10, 1924., Photostats.
  - 3. Nov 22, 1924., Photostats.
  - 4. Jan 21, 1925., Photostats.
  - 5. Feb 13, 1925., Photostats.
  - 6. Apr 8, 1925., Photostats.
  - 7. Jun 17, 1925., Photostats.
  - 8. Aug 8, 1925., Photostats.
  - 9. Nov 3, 1925., Photostats.
  - 10. Nov 12, 1925., Photostats.
  - 11. & Una, Dec 1, 1925; Photostats.
  - 12. Dec 11, 1925., Photostats.
  - 13. Dec 31, 1925., Photostats.
  - 14. & Una, 16-Jan-26; Photostats.
  - 15. Feb 5, 1926., Photostats.
  - 16. Una Jeffers, 16-Mar-26; Photostats.
  - 17. Robinson Jeffers, 13-Apr-26; Photostats.
  - 18. Apr 30, 1926., envelope.
  - 19. Oct 9, 1926., envelope.
  - 20. Nov 4, 1926.
  - MacMillan Co. to Margaret Cobb, and postcard, self-addressed., May, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Overland Monthly to Margaret Cobb, signed: B. Virginia Lee., Jan 12, 1927 and Apr 11, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series 3. Miscellaneous Manuscripts
  - STERLING POEMS - Manuscripts and printed. “At Morning”, orig. draft. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - “The House of Orchids”, orig. draft. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - “Strange Waters”, orig. draft, explanation by Rudolph Blaettler. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - “The Sailing of Keats”, orig. draft; and fragment of poem. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - “Ode to Shelley”, orig. draft. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - “Truth”, orig. draft. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - “Spontaneity 37”, orig. draft; and cartoon. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - “Balland of the Swabs”, orig. draft, explanation by Rudolph Blaettler. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - “The Testimony of the Suns”, orig. drafts, (2). (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - “Truth”, draft to Act III. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - “Hesperian”.
  - “City of Sunset”, gift of Albert M. Bender. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - “Norman Bayer”, orig. draft. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - “The Rabbit Hutch”, orig draft. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - “Yerba Buena”, “We're a-Going”, “Ballad of the Grapes”, “Raphael Weill”. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - “Romance, Romance”. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - “The Hidden Pool”. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - “To the Moon”. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - “The Iris Hill”, “Return of Faith”, and “Sleep” from “The Triumph of Bohemia”. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - “Wet Beaches”, “To Ruth Chatterton.” (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - “Lilith”, and promotion folder. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - “Sails and Mirage”, galley proof, gift of A.M. Bender. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - “The Sailing of Keats”, “Lilies of Stone”, “Remembrances of G.S.”, “In Memorium” - Bret Harte, “George Sterling - 1st Anniv.”, Abalone Song” - printed for G.S. friends, “George Sterling - 72nd Anniversary”. All printed. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Dickson, Samuel - radio script. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - “A Dream of the World,” Sterling typescript, last 5 stanzas, marginalia, Bierce. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - “A White Rose”, Sterling typescript, marginalia by Ambrose Bierce. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - CHITS OF GEORGE STERLING, AUTHOR UNKNOWN (Box 2, Folder 33a)
  - “GEORGE STERLING” facsimile of poem written in 1926 and copied in by Robinson Jeffers for Cyril Clemens, Sep-41 (Box 2, Folder 33a)
  - PERIODICALS - Book Bulletin, Overland Monthly -, Nov, Dec, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Series 4. Photographs (Box 2, Folder 35-37)
- Series 5. Clippings (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Series 6. Miscellaneous Poems and Songs (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - 1. “We're a-Going” - ptd. song.
  - 2. “You're So Beautiful”, - ptd. song, two copies.
  - 3. “Three Men That Knew Helen” - poem.
  - 4. “The Pathfinder” - original (?) & revised (?).